<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Anup Sedhain</title>
        <link>https://www.codingfreshman.com</link>
        <description>Sharing my journey as an independent software developer.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2023 16:52:40 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <image>
            <title>Anup Sedhain</title>
            <url>https://www.codingfreshman.com/favicon.ico</url>
            <link>https://www.codingfreshman.com</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>All rights reserved 2023</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What I want in life]]></title>
            <link>https://www.codingfreshman.com/articles/what-i-want-in-life</link>
            <guid>https://www.codingfreshman.com/articles/what-i-want-in-life</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Working changed my outlook on life]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My outlook on life changed three years ago. My life has been completely upended since then.</p>
<img alt="" srcSet="/_next/image?url=%2F_next%2Fstatic%2Fmedia%2Fwhat-i-want.566f082a.jpeg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 1x" src="/_next/image?url=%2F_next%2Fstatic%2Fmedia%2Fwhat-i-want.566f082a.jpeg&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75" width="2172" height="3862" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" loading="lazy" style="color:transparent"/>
<p>Before I start, let me tell you about the conversation I had with my then-girlfriend five years ago.</p>
<p>I told her, “I don’t have big dreams. A good-paying job, being able to do what I love and spending time with my family on a daily basis. That’s all I want as an adult.” And I know that I meant every word of what I said. My then-girlfriend almost flinched when she heard it.</p>
<p>She told me about how small I dreamt and that she and I couldn’t build a future together if that is what I really wanted.</p>
<p>I was sad, obviously.</p>
<p>Fast forward a couple of years and I had a job. A stable one, just as I had thought. Even paid above market price. It was not even that demanding, so I was spending ample time with people I loved. I even thought I loved what I did.</p>
<p>I really loved creating things. Bringing beautiful Figma designs to life and curating APIs that added soul to the otherwise dumb UI skeletons.</p>
<p>I was content with the bare minimum that I had achieved. Until one fine day at Himalayan Java, when my friend asked me to team up for projects that paid nothing but we would own it. I liked the ring to it. Even though it was unlike what I had imagined myself doing, I was excited and jumped right in.</p>
<p>My friend was more of a risk-taker than I ever could be. Didn’t have a stable paying job like I did but still wanted to build things for himself. I liked that about him and in ways made me want to be more like him.</p>
<p>That brought me to my era of 16-hour work days. I used to go to the office at 9 in the morning, get back at 7, and worked till 2 at night or sometimes even later.</p>
<p>The funny thing looking back to that era was that I absolutely loved it. I was excited to go to work knowing that when I get back home, I would be in a different light, different setting, working at a completely different thing that nourished my soul (cliche, I know but I don’t have other words to explain that feeling).</p>
<p>In a strange way, this made me feel like I lived two separate lives. I felt like Peter Parker as a cameraman at the office and as a Spiderman during the night. And I was successful at being both.</p>
<p>This unlocked my potential. I couldn’t have imagined working 10 hours a day and suddenly I found myself working through the day and night and doing it all over again tomorrow. I started loving who I was and what I was doing during the night time more than my day counterpart. I mean who would still love clicking pictures if they get to be a Spiderman, right?</p>
<p>I still remember it was around 1 am in the morning when I was working on logic to replace a legal template with a form data provided and had to curate a legal contract. I had been working on it for a couple days and I had finally cracked it. It was probably my most satisfying day until then.</p>
<p>A couple of weeks later, my friend and I were having a somewhat serious conversation regarding our future in Nepal. He had asked, “What is it you really want to do in your life? I told him, “I have big dreams. I want to build my own company that specializes in a niche and will be absolutely loved by at least a thousand people. That’s what I want to do.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>anup@codingfreshman.com (Anup Sedhain)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>